Okay בוקר טוב Boker Tov מועדים לשמחה Moadim L'simcha or today's דף
Daf is דף ס"ב Daf Samech Beis בבא מציעא Bava Metzia 62,
it is the דף Daf for the last day of פסח Pesach
or איסרו חג Isru Chag if you're in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
So I hope when you are listening to this it is not
יום טוב, Yom Tov, but we are recording this today, בבא מציעא
Bava Metzia 62 and we pick up at the top, it is
מיתבי Masve and then הניח להם. Hiniach Lahem. It's by the two
asterisks about 10 lines down from the top and our learning should
be in the זכות zechus of the חיילים chayalim and the חיילות
chayalot and the prayer for the real זמן גאולתנו בקרוב. zman geulateinu
bekarov.
Okay, so we are in the middle of a debate here about
whether ריבית, ribis, everybody agrees that it is not like גזל, gezel,
that money taken with ריבית ribis even ריבית דאורייתא ribis d'oreisa does
not have to be returned if it was inherited by not the
person who took it himself and there's a debate though between רב
אלעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that רב אלעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says דאורייתא ריבית d'Oraisa ribis has to be returned by the
person himself, only דאורייתא, d'oreisa and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says even
דאורייתא ריבית d'Oraisa ribis, does not have to be returned by the
person himself. So clearly it is not like גזל gezel and for
רב אלעזר Rabbi Eliezer the obligation to return it has to do
with וחי אחיך עמך v'chai achicha imach more about the relationship than
about the fact that the money itself is stolen because it isn't
stolen because it was an agreed upon contract. But as we pointed
out part of the reason there is no restitution
for רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is because it was not about just
the money that was taken, it was about the whole corrupting of
the dynamics and the power and so on and that cannot be
restored and רב אלעזר Rabbi Eliezer who says there is a מצוה
mitzvah to return the money on the person himself, that is to
try to do some type of a rectification, some type of a
way of addressing that relationship וחי אחיך עמך. v'chai achicha imach. So
that is the debate
about
ריבית דאורייתא, ribis d'oreisa, but ריבית דרבנן ribis d'rabbanan which is interestingly
called אבק ריבית avak ribis everybody agrees that there is no obligation
to return which, you know, makes if there's no consequence, you know,
could make it very tempting to transgress and as we will see
throughout this פרק perek חז"ל Chazal were well aware that many people
were lending money with ריבית, ribis at least ריבית דרבנן. ribis d'rabbanan.
Okay, so now let's take a look
מיתבי, Masve, I'll challenge you. הניח להם אביהם, Hiniach Lahem Avihem, here
we have a משנה mishna from בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, מעות של
ריבית, moes shel ribis, if their father leaves over to the children,
you know, he dies, he leaves behind in his estate money of
ריבית, ribis אף על פי שיודעו שהם של ריבית, af al pi
sheyodu shem shel ribis, even though the children know that it's ריבית
ribis, money, אינם חייבים להחזירן, einam chayavim lehachziran, they don't have to
give it back. So that's where point of departure that everybody was
assuming that the children do not have to give it back. But
the גמרא Gemara now says the inference is הא אביהן חייב להחזיר,
Ha-avian chayav lehachzir,
the inference is the father does have to give it back, that's
a proof to רב אלעזר Rabbi Eliezer that the person himself is
obligated against רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
בדין הוא דאבוהון נמי לא מיחייב להחזיר, bedin hu de'avu'un nami lo
mechayev lehachzir, really even the father does not have to give it
back. So why is it talking about the children? לדידי דקא בעי
למיתני סיפא L'aidai dikaba lemisni seifa הניח להם אביהם פרה וטלית וכל
דבר מסוים חייבים להחזיר, Hiniach Lahem Avihem par v'talis v'chol davar mesuyam
chayavim lehachzir, if their father leaves behind a cow or a טלית
talis or any specific thing, you know, that is actually can be
identified, you know, that did not belong to their father, they are
obligated to return it מפני כבוד אביהם mipnei kevod avihem because of
the honor of the father, so תני נמי רישא בדידהו. tanni nami
reisha bedit-hu. Okay, so also the first part is talking about the
children, but it's not coming to tell you the children don't have
to but the father does, the whole point of the משנה mishna
is to tell you the case in which even even the children
would have to return. By ריבית, ribis, money of ריבית, ribis nobody
has to return according to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, not the father,
not the children. But if it's a specific object that was paid
in ריבית, ribis, then the kids then they would have to return
because everybody would see that cow and say oh yeah, that's the
ריבית ribis, cow, you know, that the father took. So in order
that it does not stay in their possession and wind up impinging
on the honor of their father, if it's a specific thing, then
even the kids would have to return, return it. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this, wait a minute, הני מפני כבוד
אביהם מי מיחייב? hani mipnei kevod avihem mi mechayiv?
So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, now it's just asking on
the משנה mishna itself, you know, why are they obligated to return
because of כבוד אביהם? kevod avihem?
קרי כאן ונשיא בעמך לא תאור
בעושה מעשה עמך, Kari kan v'nasi b'amcha lo ta'or b'oseh ma'aseh amcha,
an elevated person in your nation you shall not curse and the
דרשה drasha
is בעמך בעושה מעשה עמך b'amcha b'oseh ma'aseh amcha when they do...
So when they are an upstanding person, but if somebody is a
רשע, rasha, even for their father's honor, they're not obligated to protect
their father's honor if he was a רשע, rasha, and clearly he
was a רשע rasha because he took this with רבית; ribbit; so
why, you know, now that's an interesting question in general which is
like maybe he was a צדיק tzadik in other areas, maybe this
was one area of weakness, what defines לא עושה מעשה עמך, lo
oseh ma'aseh amcha, how broad is that, maybe it's because this is
the very area that he was a רשע rasha in, so you
don't have to worry about protecting his honor. Anyway, that's the גמרא's
Gemara question. If he's somebody that lends with רבית, ribbit, why should
we be worried about protecting his honor? So the גמרא Gemara says,
כדאמר רב פנחס משמיה דרבא, ke'amar Rav Pinchas mishmeih deRava, like רב
פנחס Rav Pinchas says in the name of רבא, Rava, בשעת תשובה,
besha'at teshuvah,
he says it in a different context, that we're dealing with a
case where the father did תשובה, teshuvah, and therefore we do want
to protect his honor. So הכא נמי בשעת תשובה, hacha nami besha'at
teshuvah, so that's the case here. אי עשה תשובה, ei asah teshuvah,
says the גמרא, Gemara, מאי בעי גביה, mai bei gabeih, if he
did תשובה teshuvah why does he still have the טלית tallis or
the cow? שלא הספיק להחזיר עד שמת. shelo hispik lehachazir ad shemet.
He didn't get a chance to return it until he died. Okay,
so that's a question in that משנה, mishnah, why do you have
to worry about the honor of their father if their father was
a guy that lent with רבית, ribbit, and that raises a much
bigger question when do you protect, you know, have to care about
people's honor, what does it mean עושה מעשה עמך oseh ma'aseh amcha
or לא עושה מעשה עמך. lo oseh ma'aseh amcha. But the basic
answer to the question, does that משנה mishnah suggest that the father
returns the רבית? ribbit? The answer is not necessarily, if it's just
money, not necessarily. We're not talking about the father's obligation, we're focused
on the kids and saying there are times even the kids are
obligated. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this, מיתיבי, meitivi,
I'll ask you again about this question about whether the father's obligated
or not. הגזלנים ומלוי רבית אף על פי שגבו מחזירין, hagazlanim umalvei
ribbit af al pi shegavu machzirin, you know, thieves and people that
lend with רבית, ribbit, even if they, even after they've collected their
money, they have to give it back. So before we get to
the מחזירין machzirin which is the nature of our question, the גמרא
Gemara first wants to just parse the first part of that. גזלנים
מאי אף על פי שגבו איכא? gazlanim mai af al pi shegavu
ika? What does it mean thieves even after they've collected? If you've
lent money, you can collect the loan, but what does it mean
a thief even after he's collected? אי גזל גזל, ei gazal gazal,
if you've stolen already, you've stolen. אי לא גזל לא גזלנין קרי
ליה, ei lo gazal lo gazlanim kari leih, and if you haven't
stolen yet, you can't call the guy a גזלן. gazlan. מלוה ברבית,
malveh beribbit, you can call him a מלוה ברבית malveh beribbit before
he collected the loan, but a גזלן gazlan you could only talk
about, call him a גזלן gazlan after he's stolen.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא אימא גזלנים מאי ניהו מלוי רבית
אף על פי שגבו מחזירין. ela eima gazlanim mai nihu malvei ribbit
af al pi shegavu machzirin.
So rather read it: גזלנים, gazlanim, i.e. people who lend with רבית,
ribbit, even after they have, you know, collected their loans, not only
would we not allow them to collect, even after they collected it,
they have to give it back. Okay, now again this is interesting
because it is saying giving it back,
and which is consistent with calling them גזלנים, gazlanim, but as we
said they're not total גזלנים, gazlanim, the kids don't have to give
it back. So again this identification with גזלנים gazlanim is a fascinating
one.
But so, but that's not really a halachic point but it raises
all these questions. Clearly these are a special category, even according to
the opinion that you do give it back. Anyway, the ברייתא braita
indicates that you do give it back, which is a challenge to
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
So תנאי, tannai, okay, I can see the point, says רבי יוחנן,
Rabbi Yochanan, that תנא tanna holds you do give it back, but
I have other תנאים tannaim that agree with me that you don't
give it back. דתניא רב נחמיה ורבי אליעזר בן יעקב פוטרין את
המלוה ואת הערב מפני שיש בהן קום עשה. detanya Rav Nechemia veRabbi
Eliezer ben Yaakov potrin et hamalveh ve'et ha'arev mipnei sheyesh bahen kum
aseh. They exempt the lender and the guarantor of the loan because
there is a positive מצוה. mitzvah. Now when you say exempt and
קום עשה, kum aseh, it sounds like you're talking about מלקות. malkos.
They exempt them from getting מלקות malkos because, you know, they transgressed
a פסוק pasuk in the תורה Torah and, you know, normally by
גזל gezel we don't talk about מלקות malkos because by גזל gezel
it's a monetary aspect, it's a דבר שבממון, davar shebemamon, it's ניתן
להישבון. nitan lehishavon. But that again gets to the question of, although
רבית ribbit is a sin with money, is it about theft? Things
that are basically about theft and civil are generally not in the
category of מלקות. malkos. Here it says they would get מלקות, malkos,
but they're exempt because there's a positive מצוה. mitzvah. What's the positive
מצוה? mitzvah? Asks the גמרא. Gemara. מאי קום עשה? mai kum aseh?
לאו משום דאמרינן להו קום אהדורי? lav mishum de'amrinan lehu kum ahadori?
Isn't it that we say that they have to return it? מכלל
דתנא קמא סבר לאו בני אהדורי נינהו, michlal detanna kamma savar lav
bnei ahadori ninhu, now clearly it sounds like רב נחמיה Rav Nechemia
and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer are arguing on someone, right? It's fascinating,
we're creating another תנא tanna by implication. Since these two תנאים tannaim
say this, presumably there's another תנא tanna that disagrees, מכלל דתנא קמא
סבר לאו בני אהדורי נינהו, michlal detanna kamma savar lav bnei ahadori
ninhu, that it's not something that gets given back.
גזלנים. gazlanim. Everybody agrees that it's not a type of a גזל,
gezel, okay, and therefore it's you can talk about מלקות malkus according
to the opinion of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that there's no מצוה
mitzvah to give it back, you actually get מלקות. malkus. And then
there's another opinion that says a מצוה mitzvah to give it back,
but it's not because about השבון, heshavon, it's about קום עשה. kum
asei. There's a positive מצוה, mitzvah, like don't take the mother with
the baby birds, if you did, you know, send it free. So
here too there's a positive מצוה mitzvah that is seen as rectifying,
but it's not like compensation. Okay? So that is a nice way
of seeing this debate. Everybody agrees that it's not about stealing and
there's a question, is there a positive מצוה mitzvah to give it
back, with the ramification of do you get מלקות malkus or not?
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with it. לא. Lo.
מה
קום עשה? mai kum asei? No, what's the עשה? asei? לקרוע שטר.
likroa shtar. To tear up the שטר. shtar. So meaning we are
not talking about collecting, I'm going to read this like תוספות, Tosafot,
but collecting of the
ריבית. ribis, We're talking about the placing of the loan itself. לא
תשימון עליו נשך, lo tesimun alav neshech, that they actually transgress a
prohibition when the loan itself is made and there's ways in even
the עדים edim who signed the שטר shtar transgress, we'll see all
of this in a משנה mishnah in the end. So we're not
talking about the money that's being collected, we're talking about the loan.
The loan was made. You've transgressed לא תשימון עליו נשך, lo tesimun
alav neshech, but you can there's an עשה asei that you can
tear up the שטר. shtar. Not like a מצות עשה, mitzvot asei,
but there's something you can do that removes the debt that would
therefore mean that now you would not get מלקות. malkus. Okay. מה
קום עשה לקרוע שטר? mai kum asei likroa shtar?
מאי קסבר? mai kasavar? Now the גמרא Gemara says what does this
תנא Tanna hold? אי קסבר שטר העומד לגבות כגבוי דמי, ei kasavar
shtar ha-omed ligbos k'gavuy dami, if you hold that when you have
a שטר shtar that's it's, you know, in a position that it
can be used to collect, it's like the money has already been
collected, הא עבדי איסורא, ha avdei issura, okay, so then, you know,
then it's like the money's already been collected, what could be rectified?
ואי לאו כגבוי דמי, ve-ei lav k'gavuy dami, and if it's not
like it's been collected, הא לא עבד ולא כלום, ha lo avad
v'lo klum, nothing has happened. Meaning right now the גמרא Gemara thinks
we're still talking about not the placing of the loan, like תוספות
Tosafot sort of says, the גמרא Gemara sort of clarifying what it
meant, you know, it thinks like so it's saying if it's about
the loan, then either the loan has been collected and then we're
back to square one that, okay, can you return it by returning
the loan or not? Or the loan hasn't been collected and then
no transgression has happened yet. So the גמרא Gemara clarifies no, we're
not talking about collecting, we're talking about placing the loan. לעולם קסבר
שטר העומד לגבות לאו כגבוי דמי. le-olam kasavar shtar ha-omed ligbos lav
k'gavuy dami. והא קא משמע לן דשומא מילתא היא. ve-ha ka mashma
lan de-shuma milta hi. This is teaching you yes, it's not like
the loan has been collected, but this is teaching you that just
the placing of the loan, לא תשימון עליו נשך, lo tesimun alav
neshech, that itself is a prohibition. And that however can be rectified
or, you know, if you remove it by tearing up the שטר.
shtar. הכי
נמי מסתברא, hachi nami mistabra, that makes sense. It's not. ואלו עוברין,
ve-elu ovrin, and this finally is the משנה mishnah that is going
to clarify all the people that transgress. It would have been nice
to have started with this משנה mishnah and this comes at the
very end of the פרק. perek. ואלו עוברין בלא תעשה. ve-elu ovrin
be-lo ta'aseh. המלווה והלווה. ha-malveh ve-ha-loveh. The following people transgress: the lender,
the borrower, the creditor, the borrower, הערב, ha-arev, the the guarantor, because
if the money wouldn't have been left without a lent without a
guarantor, he was a necessary part of the process. והעדים, ve-ha-edim, and
the witnesses that sign the document. So if you're going to get
the guarantor and the witnesses, clearly the transgression is not about when
it's being paid, but there's a transgression we're talking about about when
the loan itself is being made.
בשלמא כולהו עבדי מעשה, bishlama kulehu avdi ma'aseh, and I get that
all of them could have done something and it could have been
even even the guarantor, maybe the guarantor was participating in paying it
up in the end. אלא עדים מאי עבדי? ela edim mai avdi?
What did the witnesses do in terms of the paying of the
loan? אלא לאו שמע מינה דשומא מילתא היא. ela lav shma mina
de-shuma milta hi. You see that it's about the actual placing of
the loan is the transgression. שמע מינה. shma mina. That's a good
point. Okay, so that's again showing that it's not just about גזל,
gezel, even the placing of the loan is the transgression, and then
there's a question if you place the loan but then tear up
the שטר, shtar, have you now saved yourself from the negative prohibition
in terms of the מלקות? malkus? Okay, but we have not yet
proven one way but רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, so interestingly, going back,
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan tried to infer from this that it's a
debate of תנאים Tannaim whether you have to give it back, but
in the end the גמרא Gemara says no, this is actually talking
about the placing of the loan itself. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
does not yet have a תנא Tanna that supports his position that
you do not have to give it back. But what we
have
also seen is a possible huge negative consequence that if there's no
מצוה mitzvah to give it back, then it could be that the
person will get מלקות. malkus. Okay. So now let's see where the
גמרא Gemara goes.
So the גמרא Gemara does not in the end get back to,
you know, defending רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, and in the end the
הלכה halakha is that like the position of רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar,
that ריבית קצוצה. ribbis ketzutza. that ריבית קצוצה ribis k'tzuza is יוצא
בדיינים, yotzei b'dayanim, that דאורייתא d'oreisa, ריבית ribis you actually would take
it back from the person himself, not from the kids, but from
the person himself. And now we're going to talk about a practical
application about that. אמר רב ספרא, Amar Rav Safra, said רב ספרא.
Rav Safra. כל דאילו בדיניהם מוציאין לווה למלווה, Kol de'ilu b'dineihem motzi'in
me'loveh l'malveh, it's a funny, it's looks like the same word.
בדינינו מחזירין מלווה ללווה. Bidineinu machzirin mimalveh l'loveh. Anything that בדיניהם, b'dineihem,
excuse me, anything that in the non-Jewish courts they would make the
לווה loveh have to pay the מלווה, malveh, meaning it was a
contractual agreement that he was bound to pay this interest. So anything
that's part of like a contractual agreement that in the secular courts
they would actually enforce and make the לווה loveh pay, so that
is דאורייתא d'oreisa ריבית ribbis. and therefore בדינינו bidineinu in our law
מחזירין מלווה ללווה, machzirin mimalveh l'loveh, we would give that money back
from the borrower to the lender. That's the sign of דאורייתא d'Oraisa
ריבית, ribis that it's contractually obligated and that if it were a
secular court, if it weren't for the prohibition of ריבית, ribis, he
would be bound to pay it.
Okay. כל דאילו בדיניהם אין מוציאין לווה למלווה. Kol de'ilu b'dineihem ein
motzi'in me'loveh l'malveh. Anything that in the secular law, sorry about the
background noise, anything that in the secular law they would not make
the לווה loveh pay the מלווה, malveh, meaning anything that it is
not a binding contractual agreement, בדינינו אין מחזירין מלווה ללווה, bidineinu ein
machzirin mimalveh l'loveh, we would not make him pay back. Then it
would not be דאורייתא, d'Oraisa,
you know, maybe the person gives the ריבית ribis without it being
contractually bound to do so, that would be אבק ריבית avak ribis
and we would not make him give it back. So rather than
using the word ריבית קצוצה ribis k'tzuza or ריבית דאורייתא ribis d'Oraisa
versus ריבית דרבנן ribis d'rabbanan or אבק ריבית, avak ribis, he says
the test case of whether you give it back is: is it
something that would be enforced by secular courts, is it something that
essentially there's a contractual obligation or not for the prohibition of ריבית.
ribis.
So now the גמרא Gemara questions if this nice little test case
can really work. אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף, Amar lei Abaye l'Rav
Yosef, so said אביי Abaye to רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, וכללא הוא?
V'chlala hu? Is that really a good rule? והרי סאה בסאה, V'harei
sa'ah b'sa'ah, how about a measure for measure?
דבדיניהם מוציאין לווה למלווה, De'bidineihem motzi'in me'loveh l'malveh, that in their laws
they would make the לווה loveh pay the מלווה, malveh, ובדינינו אין
מחזירין מלווה ללווה, u'bidineinu ein machzirin mimalveh l'loveh, and we don't make
him pay back, that's only דרבנן. d'rabbanan. So what's סאה בסאה? sa'ah
b'sa'ah? So this is a nice opportunity to introduce us to certain
דרבנן d'rabbanan forms of ריבית. ribis. סאה בסאה sa'ah b'sa'ah is the
classic case that somebody goes over to their friend and says, hey,
can I borrow, you know, can I borrow two eggs? And they
give them two eggs, their next door neighbor, and then they come
give them back two eggs later. What's the, what's the problem? The
problem is that when they borrowed the two eggs, maybe eggs were
going for a dime each, and now when they give them back,
maybe eggs are going for twelve cents each. So you borrowed something
that was worth ten cents and now you gave back something worth
twelve cents, that's ריבית, ribis, or not ריבית ribis but it's דרבנן
d'rabbanan a problem. Now of course you could ask a lot of
questions, which is: why should you look at everything in terms of
money? Why not just look at it at eggs? You borrowed two
eggs, you gave back two eggs.
Also clearly there was no contractual agreement to pay more, could be
that eggs would have been worth less when they were paid back,
right, so and that's a principle that the גמרא Gemara comes up
with later. If something is an equal chance of being worth less
or being worth more, then how can you be calling this ריבית
ribis even if it plays out in this particular case that it
was worth more? Okay, but one way or another, חז"ל Chazal forbade
this idea of lending סאה בסאה. sa'ah b'sa'ah. Okay, so what do
you do? So you actually go to your neighbor and say, can
I have two eggs, or you say, you know, can I, can
I borrow, I don't know, you, you turn it into money, can
I borrow two eggs and I'll pay you back twenty cents or
their equivalent and then if, and then if eggs are still worth
a dime each, anyway we can talk about all of this later.
Okay, but you're not allowed to do סאה בסאה. sa'ah b'sa'ah. So
he says, look,
אביי Abaye says, in secular law, if somebody borrowed two eggs, you
would make them pay back. Okay, so here too, so according to
you, that should be ריבית דאורייתא. ribis d'Oraisa. Anything that in secular
law they would enforce, that was a real agreement and let's say
it wasn't two eggs, let's say it was, you know, like, you
know, twenty pounds of flour and you actually had witnesses witness it.
You borrow twenty pounds of flour, you owe me to pay back
twenty pounds of flour. That's something that's legally binding if it were
not, you know, and in if it were not for ריבית ribis
and the secular courts would make you pay back and nevertheless it's
clearly ריבית דרבנן. ribis d'rabbanan. So והרי סאה בסאה דבדיניהם מוציאין לווה
למלווה ובדינינו אין מחזירין מלווה ללווה. v'harei sa'ah b'sa'ah de'bidineihem motzi'in me'loveh
l'malveh u'bidineinu ein machzirin mimalveh l'loveh.
So clearly, you know, we do not make them pay back in
that case. אמר ליה אינהו בתורת פיקדון אתא לידיה, Amar lei inhu
b'toras pikadon asa l'yadei,
so he said back to him that no, that they don't treat
this as, you know, as ריבית, ribis, meaning we also don't treat
it as ריבית, ribis, but he means that they treat it as
if As if like you were watching as if it was an
object
that you took, it's not really you borrowed, you used it, and
then you gave back a similar object. They don't treat this as
like you owe me, you borrowed something worth 20 cents and you
have to pay me back something worth 24 cents. You borrowed two
eggs, you gave back two eggs, they look at it as an
equal type of an exchange almost as if it's an object you
were watching then you gave back the same object. It's not something
labeled as
רבית. ribbis. It has to be something that's identified as interest, and
if something is identified as interest and it would be legally binding
in a secular court, that's something that we would give back. So
the גמרא Gemara says והרי משכנתא בלא נכייתא, v'harei mashkanta belo nachyata,
how about a משכנתא, mashkanta, and anybody who knows modern Hebrew, משכנתא
mashkanta is a mortgage. משכנתא mashkanta is basically you take out a
loan and you put up your property
as collateral for the loan. That's what a mortgage is, and the
בלא נכייתא belo nachyata means without deducting from the principal. So what
happens is, let's say what you put up is not your house
that you're living in, but you put up your field and I
am going to go ahead and now I lent you $10,000, your
field is collateral, I'm going to go and harvest the wheat from
that field, plant it and harvest it and get all the benefits
from it while you have yet to pay up your loan.
That's and I'm not going to deduct the wheat value from the
principal. So that's like straight רבית. ribbis. I'm getting the benefit from
having lent you the money of the produce of that field and
you're going to give me back the full amount. Now if I
deduct from the principal of the loan, that's allowed, but without deducting,
that's a case of a רבית. ribbis. Now the only difference is
that I didn't say that you have to pay me more,
and even though I contractually had rights to use it, I didn't
go ahead and have to use the field and even if I
did use the field, it could have been a year where there
was a famine or drought or who knows what and could have
been that I wouldn't have gotten anything from it. So it's not
like there's no matter what happens I'm getting a fixed amount of
interest.
So that case, even though that seems like pretty serious because it's
really a situation set up
for me to benefit from having lent you the money, that's not
דאורייתא deoraisa רבית. ribbis. It's not contractually you pay an extra $100
each month, there's a risk and I don't have to exercise my
right to it, I don't have to work the field and I
might lose money and so on. So he says והרי משכנתא בלא
נכייתא דבדיניהם מוציאין, v'harei mashkanta belo nachyata debidineihon motzi'in,
in their laws, if that was the arrangement then you would force
the לוה loveh to let the מלוה malveh take the wheat of
the field. That's legally contractually binding and that's a benefit that the
מלוה malveh gets for having lent the money. That's labeled as רבית,
ribbis, as interest.
מוציאין מלוה למלוה, motzi'in miloveh lemalveh, and now top of ס"ב עמוד
ב', Samech Beis Amud Beis, ובדיננו אין מחזירין ממלוה ללוה. uvidineinu ein
machzirin mimalveh leloveh. In their דינים dinim you take מוציאין מלוה למלוה
motzi'in miloveh lemalveh and ובדיננו אין מחזירין ממלוה ללוה. uvidineinu ein machzirin
mimalveh leloveh. In our case you don't give it back even though
it's a violation of דרבנן derabbanan רבית, ribbis, you do not give
it back because it's only דרבנן. derabbanan. So your principle doesn't work.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to him, אינהו בתורת זביני אתא
לידיה. inhu betorat zivini ata lidei. No, no, no. They don't consider
that like, oh, you have rights now to this, that's your interest
for having lent the guy the money. They say because you lent
the money you have liens on the land and that makes you
a partial owner to the land. And because you're a partial owner
of the land, you have the right to plant it and to
harvest. So it's not framed as interest being paid on the loan,
it's framed as a consequence of the liens which give you partial
ownership. So yes, it is contractually obligated in secular law, but it
is not obligated as
interest. So it's fine, you keep on carving out these exceptions, what
good is this principle going to do for us? So let's take
a look. אלא
כל שאילו בדיניהם דקאמר רב ספרא מאי אתא לאשמועינן? ella kol she'ilu
bedineihem deka'amar Rav Safra mai ata leashmi'inan? So what's he trying to
teach us with this principle if you keep on making these exceptions?
Just tell us רבית קצוצה, ribbis ketzutza, if you have a straight
case of דאורייתא deoraisa רבית, ribbis, you lend 100 and the guy
has to pay back 120, that's when you would take it out
בדיינים. bedayanim. הכי אתא לאשמועינן, hachi ata leashmi'inan, here's what he's coming
to tell us: כל שאילו בדיניהם מוציאין מלוה למלוה בדיננו מחזירין ממלוה
ללוה. kol she'ilu bedineihem motzi'in miloveh lemalveh, bedineinu machzirin mimalveh leloveh. ומאי
ניהו? umai nihu? ברבית קצוצה. beribbis ketzutza. וכדרבי אליעזר. uchedirebbe Eliezer. He's
coming to tell us that there is stuff that you would return,
things that are straight out רבית ribbis contractually, that in a secular
court you would pay, you pay interest on a loan, straight interest,
you give back the money, in our הלכה halacha we פסקן pasken
like רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer that by רבית קצוצה ribbis ketzutza it
is יוצא בדיינים. yotzei bedayanim. Again against רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*. ומאי
ניהו ריבית Ribbis, קצוצה כרבי אליעזר וכל שלא בדיניהם אין מוציאין בדיניהם
אין מחזירין ריבית Ribbis *U'maiy nei Ribbis Ketzutza ke'Reb Eliezer ve'chol she'lo
b'dineihem ein motzin b'dineihem ein machzirin Ribbis*. Now what's the second part?
Okay, beyond telling us רב אליעזר *Reb Eliezer* still, what are you
trying to tell us still by this, you know, principle seems to
be giving us, telling us some more information than we knew before?
כל שאילו בדיניהם אין מוציאין בדיננו אין מחזירין *Kol she-ilu b'dineihem ein
motzin, b'dineinu ein machzirin*. What is the type of case that you
would not give in their law and therefore would be, in secular
law, would be ריבית דרבנן Ribbis d'rabbanan, *Ribbis d'Rabbanan* and you would
not give back? ריבית Ribbis מוקדמת וריבית מאוחרת *Ribbis mukdemes ve'Ribbis me'ucheres*.
Ah, something that is clearly ריבית Ribbis, *Ribbis* but it is not
contractually obligated, okay, which is early ריבית Ribbis. *Ribbis* and late ריבית
Ribbis. *Ribbis*, which means like that it that there's no contractual obligation.
You lent me a hundred dollars, I gave you back a hundred
and twenty, okay,
or I gave you twenty dollars and then you lent me a
hundred dollars because I gave you twenty dollars. So when it is,
even if it is a hundred given and a hundred twenty given
back, if it is, what he's saying is, if it's not part
of a contractual obligation that already makes it ריבית דרבנן *Ribbis d'Rabbanan*.
So now we have some nice principles right at the beginning. There's
a prohibition even about placing the loan and it applies even to
the עדים *edim* and so on. Taking the money is not גזל
*gezel* but it seems like we פסקן *pasken* clearly that there is
an obligation, it's a prohibition but not גזל *gezel*, obligation to give
it back וחי אחיך עמך *ve'chai achicha imach*. That applies to the
person himself. That only applies to דאורייתא ריבית *d'Oraisa Ribbis*. There are
things that are and now we have also some good examples of
ריבית דרבנן *Ribbis d'Rabbanan*, things that are סאה בסאה *seah b'seah*,
equal food, objects, things that are, which feels more like just giving
back the same thing but it's דרבנן *d'Rabbanan* prohibited. Things that are
getting the use of a field that you have a mortgage on,
which is דרבנן *d'Rabbanan* because it is, again, not a contractually obligated
specific amount that's given and there could be a loss and so
on, and also something that derives from liens. So that's not the
דאורייתא ריבית *d'Oraisa Ribbis* and even actually giving back more money if
not contractually obligated and that's what רב ספרא Rav Safra *Rav Safra*
meant by it's not יוצא בדיניהם *yotze b'dineihem*, there's no contractual obligation,
that's also ריבית דרבנן *Ribbis d'Rabbanan*. Okay, and you would not give
it back if it was taken.
All right, now we finally get to the complicated line in the
משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*, so hold on to your hats. וכי אין לו
יין מה הוה *V'chi ein lo yayin mah havi*? Okay, I'm sorry,
first the quote, וכי אין לו יין מה הוה *V'chi ein lo
yayin mah havi*? Now, so the case in the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah*
to remind you of ריבית דרבנן *Ribbis d'Rabbanan*
is you go to a guy and you agree to give him,
he agrees to give you a כור kor *kor* of wheat for
twenty-five silver דינרי *dinarei* which is one gold דינר dinar. *dinar*. That's
the going rate right now when the harvest is just done and
things are at a lower rate and you buy that upfront and
it's to be delivered later. He delivers it later when things are
worth thirty. That is permissible because since you gave him the money
at that time and he had the grain or even if he
didn't have the grain it was readily available and there was a
fixed market rate, we'll see about that later, so it's like he
had the grain and it's like you already bought it. And therefore,
since it's like you already bought it, he's just delivering to you
something that is already yours even though now it is worth more.
Fine, that's okay. Then the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* goes on and says,
so that's what happened, but then you said, but then he said,
look, I don't have the wheat on me right now, let me
let's say it's now worth thirty, so I'll owe you thirty, and
it sounds like that's okay to say because if you could have
given the wheat, you can now give thirty, even though you got
twenty-five, so it's already sounding pretty funny, but actually that's okay. But
then he says, but instead, you know what, I'll pay, I'll pay
you back wine, I know you want to use it now to
buy wine and wine now is cheap and wheat is expensive so
you want to do that, so I'll owe you that wine, okay,
thirty דינרי *dinarei* would get you I don't know thirty jugs of
wine, I will owe you thirty jugs of wine instead of the
כור *kor* of wheat. And the only problem, says the משנה Mishnah.
*Mishnah*, is he doesn't have wine and therefore what's going to happen?
He's going to pay back the wine in a month from now
when the wine is not worth thirty דינרי *dinarei* but fifty דינרי
*dinarei* and that's like, it makes it like he borrowed thirty, he
says I owe you the thirty, let me keep the thirty, I'll
owe you the wine instead, it's like he borrowed thirty and gave
back fifty because it sounds like from the משנה mishna. *Mishnah* he
doesn't have the wine. If he had the wine, it would be
like a replay of what we had by the wheat, then it
would be okay, it's like the seller already has the wine and
and it's like he already sold the wine and then he'll just
deliver it later. But because he doesn't have the wine, so he's
now taking the thirty obligation to pay back wine later that he
doesn't have now and that's a problem because then it's going to
be worth more.
So what if he doesn't have wine? ותניא *Ve-tanya* אין פוסקין על
פירות
עד שיצא השער
*ein poskin al perot ad she-yetzei ha-sha'ar*.
You do not go ahead and make this arrangement to give you
fruit later on until the market until the market price has been
set. עד שיצא השער *Ad she-yetzei ha-sha'ar*. יצא השער פוסקין אף על
פי שאין לזה יש לזה *Yatza ha-sha'ar poskin af al pi she-ein
le-zeh yesh le-zeh*. But once the market price has been set, you
can make this arrangement and even if you don't have the object,
other people have it. So that's what I was saying earlier about
the case by the כור *kor* of wheat. You can agree, the
price now is 25 silver dinare per כור *kor*, you can agree
to provide that, and the guy gives you the 25 dinare and
you can deliver it later, even if you don't have any wheat,
since there's a fixed market price and since everybody is selling wheat
and it's readily available, it's like you already bought it. So you
see, once the market price is set and it's readily available, you
don't have to have it. So why is it a problem in
the משנה mishna *Mishnah*? So when you convert that to wine also
the market price is set, who needs it, who needs you to
have wine? The משנה mishna *Mishnah* says you don't have wine, but
who needs you to have wine? אמר רבא Rava מתניתין בבא לחוב
בדמיה עסקינן *Amar Rava matnitin be-ba lachov be-dameha askinan*. Our משנה mishna.
*Mishnah*,
the difference in our משנה mishna *Mishnah* is that in the first
case the guy was buying the wheat paid the 25 silver dinare.
Here, no money is actually being given. The guy says, I owe
you this wheat, it's worth 30, okay, so it'll be instead of
the 30 I'll give you wine. So that is a problem because
if he had been given 30 and says I'll provide you the
wine later, that's fine. But he wasn't given the 30 money, he
was just like that debt I'm now going to pay in wine.
And the reason that it's okay when you don't have the stuff
in your possession is if the guy gave me 25 silver dinare,
I can go ahead right now and go to my next-door neighbor
farmer and buy it from him. So that can make it seem
like I already have that and like he already purchased it from
me when he gave me the money, because the market price is
set and it's readily available and I have the money. But רבא
Rava *Rava* says the problem in our משנה mishna *Mishnah* is I
don't have the wine and I don't have any money in hand,
and that's the problem in our משנה mishna. *Mishnah*. מתניתין בבא לחוב
בדמיה עסקינן *Matnitin be-ba lachov be-dameha askinan*, וכדתניא *ve-chi-detanya* like we taught
in a ברייתא Beraita *Baraita*: הרי שהיה נושה בחבירו מנה *Harei she-haya
nosheh ba-chavero maneh*. So this guy owed you a hundred dollars and
this farmer and you went there to the threshing floor, והלך ועמד
על גורנו *ve-halach ve-amad al gorno*, ואמר תן לי מעותי שאני רוצה
ליקח בהם חטים *ve-amar ten li me'otai she-ani rotzeh likach bahem chitim*.
And he said, okay, give me my hundred dollars. Now it's the
market, the people are selling wheat and it's at the lowest price
and I want to go buy wheat. אמר לו חטים יש לי
שאני נותן לך *Amar lo chitim yesh li she-ani noten lach*. He
said, look, I don't have the hundred dollars but I do have
wheat, so I'll give you a hundred dollars worth of wheat at
the price it is right now. צא ועשם עלי כשער של עכשיו
*Tzei ve-aseim alai ke-sha'ar shel achshav*. Go figure out what the going
rate is, and now it's at the lowest going rate, and let's
say a hundred dollars right now will get you ten bushels of
wheat, I'll give you ten bushels of wheat. ואני אעלה לך כל
שנים עשר חודש *Ve-ani a'aleh lecha kol shneim asar chodesh*. And I'll
provide you from this wheat for the entire, for the entire month.
אסור *Assur*. That's forbidden. Why? Didn't that sound just like the case
of our משנה mishna *Mishnah*? דלאו כאיסרא דאתי לידיה דמי *De-lav ke-issara
de-ati le-yadeih dami*. It's not like the איסרא *issara*, it's not like
the coin has come to his hand. The reason in our משנה
mishna. *Mishnah* it's okay is because the guy actually has the
it's readily available, there's a fixed market price, and he has the
money to buy it. But this ברייתא braita *Baraita* teaches if you
don't have money in your hand, it's not okay. All right, the
only thing is that this ברייתא *Baraita* says it's even not okay
even if you have the wheat. Our משנה mishna *Mishnah* says it's
a problem because he didn't have the wine, that it would have
been okay if you actually had the produce, which makes sense. If
you have the produce, you don't need the money in hand. So
let's see what the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says. אמר ליה אביי Abaye
*Amar lei Abaye*. אביי Abaye *Abaye* said back to him: אי דלאו
כאיסרא דאתי לידיה דמי מאי איריא אין לו אפילו יש לו נמי
*Ei de-lav ke-issara de-ati le-yadeih dami mai irya ein lo afilu yesh
lo nami*? So that's what אביי Abaye, *Abaye* says back. If you
basically cannot make this arrangement when you're not getting money in hand,
so then it's a problem even if you do have the produce,
it doesn't work. And that's a little strange and we're going to
teach later actually that there's a ברייתא *Baraita* that actually says no,
either is enough, either money in hand or you actually have the
produce. But this ברייתא *Baraita* at least says that without the money
in hand we don't allow this. That gets too close to ריבית
*ribbis*. If the guy gave you money, then you can give him
back the produce later even if it's worth more. That's more like
purchase, that's not like ריבית *ribbis*. But if he's not giving you
money, you just owe him money and then you're going to pay
it back later when it's worth more, so that starts with a
debt and it ends. ends with giving back something worth more than
the debt, that's a problem. So if you're not getting money right
now, getting money right now makes it a purchase, if you're not
getting right now says this ברייתא says it's a purchase. So then
the משנה mishna should have been a problem even if he had
the wine. So that's not going to be a good explanation of
the משנה. mishna So let's see what אביי Abaye, says.
אלא אמר אביי, Ella Amar Abaye, rather אביי Abaye, says, מתניתין כדתני
רב ספרא בריבית דבי רבי חייא. Masnisin k'detanei Rav Safra b'Ribbis d'Bei
Rabbi Chiya. Our משנה mishna is like the ברייתא that רב ספרא
taught when in the ריבית, you know, teachings of רבי חייא, Rabbi
Chiya, the collection of ריבית ברייתות Beraitas of רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya.
דתני רב ספרא בריבית דבי רבי חייא יש דברים שהם מותרים ואסורים
מפני הערמת ריבית. Detanei Rav Safra b'Ribbis d'Bei Rabbi Chiya yesh devarim
she'heim muttarim v'assurim mipnei ha'aramas Ribbis. There are some things that really
should be permissible in principle, but they're forbidden because they are הערמת
ריבית, ha'aramas Ribbis, like a deception, a way of getting around ריבית
with a wink and a nod, which seems to be different from
אבק ריבית. avak Ribbis. Okay, seems to be lighter than that, but
still we're, okay, so but that's what we're going to be talking
about. כיצד? Keitzad? אמר לו הלווני מנה. Amar lo halveni maneh. So,
you know, ראובן Reuven says to שמעון, Shimon, lend me a hundred
dollars. אמר ליה מנה אין לי. Amar lei maneh ein li. שמעון
Shimon says, I don't have a hundred dollars on me. חיטין במנה
יש לי שאני נותן לך. Chittin b'maneh yesh li she'ani notein lach.
But you know what? I have
wheat worth a hundred dollars. Okay. נתן לו חיטין במנה. Nassan lo
chittin b'maneh. So he gave him the wheat and he says, I'm
giving you a hundred dollars worth of wheat, you owe me a
hundred dollars.
Then וחוזר ולקח הימנה בעשרים וארבע סלע. v'chozer v'lakach heimenna b'esrim v'arba
sela. And then שמעון Shimon came and said, oh, you know what?
I just found twenty-four סלע. sela. Twenty-four is like ninety-six or twenty-four
or whatever. Okay, so let's just say, let's go back, let's call
it twenty-five and twenty-four.
So okay, he says, you know what? I don't have any money
but here, I can lend you twenty-five סלע sela worth of wheat.
You owe me twenty-five סלע. sela. Fine. He gives him the wheat.
Then he says, oh my gosh, look at this! I just found
that I have twenty-four סלע. sela. Will you sell me your wheat
for twenty-four סלע? sela? He says, sure. Sells him the wheat for
twenty-four סלע. sela. What do you have now? That now ראובן Reuven
has twenty-four סלע sela in cash, which is what he wanted. He
wanted cash, he didn't want wheat. But he owes שמעון Shimon twenty-five
סלע sela because שמעון Shimon lent him twenty-five סלע sela worth of
wheat. Okay, so that is a way that you've with a wink
and a nod, you've managed to get it that שמעון Shimon gave
ראובן Reuven twenty-four סלע sela and but ראובן Reuven owes him twenty-five.
Alright, so וחוזר ולקח הימנה בעשרים וארבע סלע מותר. v'chozer v'lakach heimenna
b'esrim v'arba sela muttar. Technically that's מותר, muttar, ואסור
לעשות כן מפני הערמת ריבית. v'assur la'asos ken mipnei ha'aramas Ribbis. It's
forbidden to do that because it is a ריבית, it is a
deception around ריבית. So actually everything there is technically מותר muttar as
opposed to things that are actually ריבית דרבנן, but here
חזל Chazal
did not allow it because clearly you are doing it with a
wink and a nod. הכא נמי כגון דאמר. Hacha nami k'gon de'amar.
So that's the case of our משנה. mishna He said, הלווני שלושים
דינרים, halveni shloshim dinarim, lend me thirty דינרים. dinarim. Okay. אמר ליה
שלושים דינרים אין לי. Amar lei shloshim dinarim ein li.
I don't have thirty דינרים. dinarim. חיטין בשלושים דינרים יש לי שאני
נותן לך. Chittin b'shloshim dinarim yesh li she'ani notein lach. But I
have wheat worth thirty דינרים dinarim that I'll give to you. נתן,
Nassan, and then you'll owe me thirty דינרים. dinarim. נתן לו חיטין
בשלושים דינרים. Nassan lo chittin b'shloshim dinarim. He gave him grain worth
thirty דינרים dinarim and he owed him thirty דינרים. dinarim. וחוזר ולקח
הימנה בדינר זהב. v'chozer v'lakach heimenna b'dinar zahav.
And then שמעון Shimon turned around and said, oh my gosh, look
at this! Here's in my pocket a דינר זהב, dinar zahav, twenty-five
silver דינר. dinar,
You know, I will
buy that off of you now. If you'll, will you sell me
those thirty whatever, you know, will you sell me that wheat that
you just bought that I just lent you for thirty דינר, dinar?
will you sell it to me for twenty-five דינר? dinar So אי
אית ליה חמרא ללווה דיהיב ליה בשלושים דינר פירא הוא דקא שקיל
מיניה ולית לן בה. ee is lei chamra l'loveh d'yahiv lei b'shloshim
dinar peira hu d'ka shakal minei v'leis lan bah.
So here's how it could be okay. It could be okay that
he would say that he would say, you know, sell him the
wheat back, get the twenty-five דינר dinar. in your pocket. Now ראובן
Reuven owes him thirty דינר. dinar But if he could pay him
back that thirty דינר dinar with produce, with wine, then we wouldn't
be concerned about הערמת ריבית. ha'aramas Ribbis. Again, technically everything is okay.
Lent him thirty דינר dinar. worth of wheat, then bought the wheat
off of him for twenty-five דינר. dinar No one action was a
problem, but it's a trick. So we would let that trick go
if the original loan of the thirty דינר dinar of wheat was
paid back with thirty דינר dinar of wine. He got wheat in
the beginning, he gave back wine. Yes, in the end what really
happened was that he got twenty-five דינר dinar in his pocket and
he gave the guy thirty דינר of wine, but technically everything was
okay and we will allow that. That looks more like, you know,
commerce than it does like ריבית. אי אית ליה חמרא לאו ועביד
ויהיב ליה בשלשים דינרא פירי הוא דקא שקיל מיניה
Ee is lay chamra
lav ve'avid veyav lay bishloshim dinara pairay hu dekashakil minay
he's taking from him produce and that would not bother us. ואי
לא, Ve'ee lo, but if he doesn't and he winds up giving
back to him thirty dinara
because he owes him thirty dinara because of originally the wheat he
took, ואי לא כיון דלית ליה חמרא ודאי משקל זוזי מיניה ve'ee
lo keivan deleis lay chamra vadai mishkal zuzay minay he'll wind up
taking from him not wine but money, מחזי כרבית meichzi keribbis and
therefore it looks like רבית ribbis because שמעון Shimon gave him a
twenty-five dinari and he gave him back thirty dinari and that's the
הערמת רבית. ha'aramas ribbis. That's the problem of our משנה. mishna Now
that's a nice interesting principle.
It's interesting that the משנה mishna would call it מרבית, marbis, which
is actually the first case the משנה mishna would identify as רבית
דרבנן ribbis derabbanan would be something that we're actually saying is technically
מותר mutar and it's really just הערמת רבית. ha'aramas ribbis. But the
bigger problem is that those words cannot, that case cannot fit at
all in the words of the משנה. Mishna. So אמר ליה רבא,
amar lay Rava, רבא said back to him, אי הכי תן לי
חטי דמי חטי מיבעי ליה. ee hachi tein lee chitei demai chitei
miba'ei lay. In our משנה שמעון Shimon is coming and saying give
me the grain I bought from you for twenty-five dinari. According to
you אביי, Abaye he should be saying give me the money
for the grain I lent you. I lent you twenty-five dinari of
grain, pay me back the money, not give me the grain. So
תני דמי חטי, tani demai chita, fine, amend the text, have it
say give me back the money for the wheat that I gave.
שאני מוכרן, shani mocharan, שמכרתים לך. she'machartim lach.
Okay
fine, now רבא says, but one minute, it says שאני מוכרן, shani
mocharan, שמכרתים לך מיבעי ליה. she'machartim lach miba'ei lay.
The משנה says give me the wheat, I want to sell it
to buy wine. That's the case of the משנה. According to you
אביי, Abaye it should say give me the money for the wine
that I sold to you. So תני שמכרתים לך. tani she'machartim lach.
Okay fine, switch it to mean that I sold to you. Okay,
you could say that he sold to him, I was saying that
he lent to him the wheat for a hundred or for
twenty-five, but you could also sort of say that he sold him
the wheat for a hundred and twenty-five and then he sold it
back for less. Either way though, he winds up with a debt.
All right. שמכרתים לך. she'machartim lach. הרי חטים עשויין לך עלי בשלשים
דינרים, harei chitim asuyin lacha alay bishloshim dinarim, one minute, the משנה
says that ראובן Reuven says to שמעון, Shimon, you know that wheat
I owe you? Now it'll be a thirty dinar debt. Used to
be twenty-five, now it's thirty. That's the case of the משנה. מעיקרא
נמי הכי אוקימנא ליה, me'ikara nami hachi okiminan leih,
but according to you אביי, Abaye, that was the original case, that
when he sold him or lent him the grain he did it
for thirty shekel. It's not now being converted into thirty dinar.
הכי קאמר ליה, hachi ka'amar leih,
so אביי Abaye is saying, okay, that's what he means, בדמי חטיך
שעשית עלי בשלשים דינר. bedamei chitecha she'asita alay bishloshim dinar.
What ראובן Reuven is saying to שמעון Shimon is not now we're
going to owe you thirty, but we're completely changing the case. Not
give me the wheat you owe me, but give me the money
for the wheat I sold you. And I sold, and now ראובן
Reuven is saying back to שמעון, Shimon, I owe you thirty for
the wheat that you sold to me. Not now let's make it
into a debt of thirty. All right. הרי לך אצלי בהן יין
ויין אין לו, harei lacha etzli bahein yayin veyayin ein lo,
okay but then the משנה says that ראובן Reuven says, okay and
that thirty I owe you, I'll pay you in wine, but I
don't have wine. Okay? So it says והא בדינר זהב כור וכן
השאר קתני. veha bedinar zahav kor vechein hashar katani.
I'm sorry, oh that's how it ends, הרי לך אצלי בהן יין
ויין אין לו, harei lacha etzli bahein yayin veyayin ein lo, so
that's still אביי's read. Now I owe you thirty and I would
have to give it to you in wine, but I don't have
the wine right now. And if he could give it to him
in wine, it would not be a problem of הערמת רבית. ha'aramas
ribbis. So then the גמרא gemara finally says והא בדינר זהב כור
וכן השאר קתני. veha bedinar zahav kor vechein hashar katani. But one
minute, the משנה right at the beginning says that they agreed on
twenty-five dinari for the כור and that was the going rate. And
according to you אביי, the whole scenario is that it was sold
at thirty dinari, not at twenty-five silver dinari, at thirty dinari, and
that was the going rate, and then it was sold back at
twenty-five dinari, sold back at a discount. So clearly with all your
emendations, you cannot get around the fact that the משנה is not
the way you are describing it. So what the גמרא is going
to do, so now what we've done is we have one way
of explaining the משנה that this idea of agreeing to
provide produce later on is okay, but it's only okay if you're
given the money now and it's a type of a purchase rather
than a type of a loan
and that can't have been the read of the משנה because the
משנה sounds like had he had the wine it would have been
okay, but in the case of the משנה he wasn't getting money,
he was just converting a debt that he had because of the
wheat. So that read of the משנה didn't work. אביי gives this
whole other case of a way you could do with a wink
and a nod you could sell something and buy. Back, or loan
it and buy it back, and create, and that is a problem
of הערמת ריבית, Ha'aramas Ribbis, but there's no way that that can
be read in the משנה. So tomorrow we're going to go back
and to the first approach, which is certainly much closer to the
פשט, pshat, and find out that there's another ברייתא that actually would
allow a case even if no money is being given now, if
the person actually has the produce to provide. Okay, so we will
end with this now.